minute or so for everything to get
moving forward. The recording is
started. I'm admitting everybody from
the uh waiting room. So, good morning
everybody. Uh it usually does uh take a
minute or so for everybody who is in the
lobby uh or the waiting room to join
into the meeting. So, while that occurs,
I'll do my usual introduction. I'm
Dominic Zerlo and I'm the director for
the New Mexico Department of Health
Center for Medical Cannabis and
Psilocybin. And as a reminder, this
meeting is recorded, so please remember
to use appropriate language during the
meeting. Um, and uh this is the dosage
administration and clinical practice
committee with Ian Dunn as the chair.
And with that, I will turn it on over to
Ian. So Ian, the meeting is yours.
>> Good morning everyone. My name is Ian
Dunn. I am the chair of the dosage
administration and clinical practice
committee. Welcome everyone. Just as a
quick reminder, committees operate in an
advisory capacity to the board. They
provide forum for individuals who may be
experts but may not serve on the board
due to real or perceived conflicts of
interest. And the committee support the
board by expanding community input,
incorporating subject matter expertise,
and increasing participation in program
development. So on our last meeting of
this committee we had adopted the uh
psychological and administrative
preparation guidelines. So now we are
going to look at the administration
guidelines um for this program. Again
these are kind of optimal situations
what we would like to see happen. um
they're not going to necessarily be in
the rules, but they are just uh a view
of what we expect to happen during these
administration sessions.
So last meeting we had preliminarily
began um parsing the requirements for
dosing and supervision. So um what we
have
and is that they we have to confirm the
informed consent that clarification was
added that the right to postpone cancel
or delay a session at any time uh prior
to the actual administration.
Um
perfect. And then you'll go ahead and
see it on screen. Sorry that took a
second to pull up.
All righty.
>> Thank you. Um the purpose of these is to
involve the supervised facilitation of
patients medical psilocybin experience
with an improved setting. Um so they
provides a safe and supportive
environment. Maintain patient physical
and psychological safety. Support the
patient during altered states of
consciousness. Monitor the psychological
or physiological and psychological
responses during administration. Ensure
compliance with regulatory and facility
safety requirements. Facilitate a
therapeutic environment conducive to
introspection, emotional processing and
insight. And administration sessions
should occur after the completion of
preparation sessions and prior to post
session integration.
So um now I will go ahead and um allow a
little bit of discussion on the minimum
administration requirements. This is
where we had left off on our last
meeting. So I just want to give um any
opportunity to speak on it. Currently
what we have is administration must
occur within an approved setting. The
facilitator and psychedelic therapist
must be present and available to provide
support for during for the duration of
the administration session and the
administration must be documented in the
patients clinical record. Administration
sessions must comply with all applicable
state regulations, facility policies and
safety protocols.
Any questions, comments, concerns so
far?
Cool.
So before [clears throat] they are going
to be administered their psilocybin, we
need to confirm their um informed
consent. So we need to confirm that the
patient understands the nature of
psilocybin administration. We need to un
ensure that they understand the
potential psychological and physical
effects. The possible intensity or
unpredictability of the experience. The
patient's right to postpone, cancel or
delay a session at any time before
administration. Notification that the
administration session is not covered by
insurance. Show the patient the patient
bill of rights. Um patient
confidentiality form shall be signed for
administration. We should reaffirm those
boundaries that we set in preparation
related to um touch, related to all
boundaries that we've set as a patient,
what you are okay with, what you aren't,
what modalities you accept. Um and
consent confirmation must be documented
prior to administration. So any
questions, comments, concerns on the
informed consent confirmation.
All righty.
So the dosage and administration. So
psilocybin products must be administered
according to the psychedelic therapist's
guidance and recommendation. So
administration procedures should include
verification of the product identity and
dosage confirmation that the product was
obtained through authorized channels
documentation of the dosage
administrated uh observation of
ingestion or administration by the
patient and the patients must
voluntarily self- administer the
product. I remember last time Denali had
brought up that this may not work for
all patients. Oh, she actually has her
hand up. Um Denali
And then Denali, your mic has been
enabled.
>> Thank you. Um yeah, thanks for
remembering. And we had some email
conversation um about it too. I think um
the recommendation
we we talked to some folks from end of
life options and I learned more about
how this works in medical aid and dying.
And while we do still require
self-administration,
we don't prohibit help with
self-administration. And so, um, I I
think it would be helpful to have that
explicit. So, I'll put some language in
the chat, but also read it here. Um, I
don't know why it's like that here. Hold
on. Um,
so, a patient must voluntarily
self-administer the product, which is
what you have here. I would add the
clause, if a patient requires assistance
with self- administration, the provider
and patient must discuss the need for
assistance in advance and document an
appropriate administration assistance
plan. And then I think it would be
helpful for providers and liability just
if we get in the practice of adding some
disclaimers about um criminal liability.
So I I'm going to recommend adding
documenting an appropriate
administration plan shall not constitute
assisting in the possession,
distribution, or manufacturing of a
controlled substance.
And I'm bad at multitasking, but am
putting this [laughter] in the chat now.
And I think the criminal I just I'm
lawyer brain so I love the [snorts]
added protection but you know the
medical psilocybin act does have this
protection for providers from criminal
liability. So, if we want to just keep
it at the um requirement for documenting
a plan, I think that that would be
sufficient.
>> Yeah, I think cuz they already waved
those for the providers in the law, it
wouldn't be necessary. But, um I did put
the other part before
that they must that they if they require
assistance that they can ask for it
essentially in prettier words.
Thank you.
>> Of course. Any other concerns?
All righty. So, facilitator monitoring
and support. So, facilitators must
remain present and attentive throughout
the administration session. That doesn't
mean that they are, you know, in the
room like watching them, eye contact,
that would be a little uncomfortable. It
just means that if they were if they had
um like a call light or some other
mechanism that the facilitator would be
available and could be accessed if
that's what the patient requested. So
their responsibilities would obviously
be observing patient behavior and
emotional response. Um providing
reassurance and grounding support when
needed, monitoring for signs of distress
or adverse reactions, maintaining a calm
and supportive presence. And
facilitators should generally allow
patients to experience the session
internally, offering guidance only when
necessary to maintain safety or
stability.
And then Denali
also I saw Skye's post and I will go
ahead and start posting it in the chat.
I
apparently am a little scatterbrain this
morning. So I am sorry everyone. Here's
what we've gone over so far.
Oh, that did not copy everything. Love
that.
There we go.
All righty. And then Denali,
this might be a question for the
department. I just want to make sure
that the guidelines that we're
developing are consistent with the rules
that they're proposing. I I think that
there was a requirement in the draft
proposal rules that there be two people
and I [clears throat] yeah I just I'd
like to know from the department what
the perspective is on you know whether
they need to be physically in the room
um
and [clears throat] yeah am I
understanding the requirement from the
draft rules correct that it is requ
there's two people must be present and
what what are we defining as presence
Um
>> so Denali uh and Ian I can answer that.
Um and uh and what we've actually done
in other situations where um there just
need to be two people present and that's
in part from a safety standpoint. Um but
the other aspect with that is you know
the the individual the patient for
example could be behind a screen or
something like that that we just need to
ensure that there are staff that are
there and that are present in some sort
of a way to ensure that if there is an
issue or a problem that they're there
and they're available. Um but it doesn't
mean they need to be, you know, like
staring the person right in the face
kind of a thing. I hope that's helpful.
and and it could conceivably as long as
they're there be like in the hallway
with the door open just so that the
patient gets a little additional privacy
or something like that. Does that make
sense?
>> Yeah, it does. And I um unless
[clears throat] other folks have
thoughts that feels flexible enough to
meet the individual needs of folks.
>> Thank you. And Lisa, your mic has been
enabled.
Oh hi. Um uh I would love to get a
little bit more clarification on the two
people requirement. Do they have to be
present in the
facilitation room or they have to be
present in a medical office?
>> In a medical office. So, uh, like kind
of how Dominic was saying, it could be,
um, people, you know, with the doors
open. Um, but it would not necessarily
like two people. I think two people
staring me down when I'm not on
psilocybin is uncomfortable. So, I can
only imagine what it would feel like to
be in a room. Um, and just have two
people watching you constantly. So, I
wanted to provide a little bit of
flexibility. Um, I know in hospitals
like what they'll do is they'll put the
the nursing station outside their
patients rooms. Um, and so they can see
in and they can make sure that they're
okay, but they're not staring at them
and staring them down cuz that can that
makes people feel uneasy in general.
Um, Maya, your mic has been enabled.
>> Hi, thanks. So, I am a physician
researcher at UNM, work with Dr. Leman
and others. And I may have um missed
this. I I'm assuming there is the option
to have people sitting in the room with
them. Uh that is certainly how we do all
of our studies. Two people in the room
with the patient now or the participant,
I should say. In our cases, the
participant typically has their eye
shades on. and they've got, you know,
that music on. I've never had, and not
to say that it couldn't occur, but in
that type of setting, I've never had
somebody say that they were
uncomfortable having people in the room
with them. It's it's standard for pretty
much all the research out there. And um
I I I doubt that that is prohibited in
the wording. But um I just wanted to say
that it is absolutely okay, often
therapeutic and sometimes really the
best way to go about it. So just wanting
to confirm that there's no language
prohibiting that type of scenario,
>> right? So the the facilitator has to be
present and attentive. So being in the
room absolutely you are present and
attentive throughout the session that
works great. Um but there are there may
be a patient who that makes
uncomfortable and so we just wanted to
provide them an option not to say that
they aren't going to be monitored. We
have to make sure that they are safe but
to make sure that if they need a little
bit of space that we can give them that
especially when we are giving them
profound altered states of
consciousness. Um so we just it's just a
comfortability thing. I would I if they
are prefer that and I'm sure there are
patients that do um
then they would be free to have someone
monitor them the entire time.
>> Great. I just would emphasize the safety
though if you're not directly in the
room with them. I mean, I have heard of
situations where the patients become
runners and so you want to be able to
ensure the safety of the participant
slashpatient
even if you're not directly in the room
with them. I think that's evident to
everyone, but I just wanted to sort of
speak it out loud.
>> Yes, thank you. And Katherine, your mic
has been enabled.
Good morning everybody. Um, so I just
wanted to kind of clarify. You said just
somebody in the building. I don't know
if I agree with that. I think it needs
to be somebody that can come in and help
out if necessary. So like I don't think
just having like a receptionist hanging
out in the building is going to be a
good backup in case something like in
case the the primary person needs to use
the restroom or you know something they
need to do something. I think the second
person needs to be able and willing and
understand what psychedelics are or
psilocybin is so [snorts] that they can
come and help out in appropriately. Um,
so I just want to kind of make that
clear. And then I also just want to say
that my experience has been the opposite
in that I often times come in to the
room and I'm told that I'm interrupting
and that to please leave. Um, especially
when the medicine is full force and
they're having epiphies and insights, I
offer to be there as much as they want
me to be there, but I also offer to
leave the room as much as they want me
to leave the room. I do make sure to
check in on them every um depending on
where they are in their journey. It's
every 15 to 30 minutes like I lay eyes
on them, but they do have call buttons
and I do make sure that I'm there when
they need me when they want me and I'm
not interfering with their journey. So I
think I have had clients who want me to
sit with them the entire time and I'm
fine doing that. Um but I can't say that
all clients want people there all the
time. So, I I think it is important,
Ian, and I appreciate that you have
language in there that allows for that,
but I think what I'm mostly concerned
about is making sure that the second
person can actually step in if needed.
Like, if the facilitator has a heart
attack, what are we going to do? Have
the reception come in and, you know,
take over? It needs, right? So right now
it uh of those two people it either has
to be like a psychedelic therapist and a
facilitator or
>> um
like a psychedelic therapist overseeing
two facilitators but it's not it'll
never be like well the USPS guy just
walked in so we technically have two
people in the building like that'll
never happen. Okay. Um it has to be
someone that has been licensed through
the medical program. Um, but thank you.
That would be a really big concern
because that that would be a safety
issue.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you. And then Gregory, your mic
has been enabled.
>> Greetings. Um, and welcome May. It's
good to see you here. Um, the on this
last note, I think the best language
would be like practitioners that are
included in the treatment plan, right?
So we all we have to have a plan. The
people that are involved are going to be
on that list. UPS guys is not involved.
Um what I one thing I was concerned
about was um
just the language around egress. Um and
so I was just reminded recently of the
tragedy in Denver where [clears throat]
the guy jumped off the balcony.
total like like the layers of
incompetence that led to that are
astounding, but like in [clears throat]
our context, we're not going to have
like, you know, people in a hotel room
unsupervised or whatever like that, but
like allowing for the flexibility of of
IP and independent practice and context
and everything like Katherine is
describing. And I believe Katherine, if
I understand, uses like a call button.
Um, and I think with consent, video
surveillance, stuff like that, like
observability and safety like just need
to be paramount. I don't know how to
write the language. Denali is here for
that. [laughter]
Um,
uh, but are we taking into consideration
group? So like the context of group and
individual therapies are going to be
different in practice. And do we need to
be
set our observation standards with
greater physical presence when there's
more people involved in this room
currently dosing like multiple patients
or multiple participants? Um,
it just seems like
human like I don't know like with an
individual if I'm alone [clears throat]
I think like the safety factor of being
alone in a room is different than if
there are other people in the room cuz
someone else could get weird and then if
there is like a single point of egress I
think monitoring that egress is
sufficient for like quote unquote a
runner
as opposed to if there's like another
way out of the room.
I don't know if that's
>> Yeah. And I think that's one of the
reasons why we wanted to have two people
in the building is that if someone had
like an adverse event adverse reaction,
it doesn't even have to be running away.
It could just be something like um they
got nauseous and threw up. Um if that
were to happen and then someone else had
an adverse event,
then there would be no one to get them
if there was only one person in the
room. So, I think we try to avoid that
by adding that extra person to say,
"Hey, worst case scenario, we can have
one of us go run and grab the person and
then one of us can stay and make sure
that everything is okay. Um, ideally, no
one would run, but it's the real world
and people react to substances in
different ways and um we just have to be
prepared. So, I think we try to mitigate
by having extra facilitators. I think it
gets weird because it is very hard to
write
regulations to keep people in a room.
Um,
>> padded cell.
[gasps]
um without like
without bringing up the like potential
for judicial complication of kidnapping
like we would just have to basically say
we are going to make sure and keep you
as safe as possible.
I mean in an ideal world do we just put
cyclocks? No.
>> That that would be expensive and
burdensome but and probably unsafe in a
fire. But um
we it's just a it's a balancing game. So
I think we're trying to do that with the
facilitators, but if we need to add
more, we definitely can.
>> Well, I think with legal defensibility,
it's the concept of observability like
>> use your as a business as like do your
use your best judgment and we can have
ideas and guidelines and practices,
right? But like when it comes to the
actual rules, leaving room for people to
make the decision in the best interest
of the patient, I think we, you know,
and don't let me say that we're going to
be able to trust people, but like I want
to be able to trust people.
>> Absolutely. And I think we
have to and some at some point in any
program, we have to trust someone. It's
unfortunate, but we always there's no
way to get great things accomplished
just one person. There's always
assistance. So, it's always going to be
that game of can I can I trust these
people? And it will always be hopefully
yes.
Uh Lisa,
I believe your mic is enabled. Cool.
>> Thank you. Um I have a question about
the last bullet point. Facilitators
should generally allow patients to
experience the session internally
offering guidance only when necessary.
Um my question is about what type of
guidance uh are facilitators allowed to
provide a therapy during the session and
if not then maybe we should use
nondirective facilitation
when necessary.
>> Yeah. So I just want to make sure I
understand. So um you want to change the
offering guidance to offering
nondirective
facilitation or did I get that?
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Got you.
All righty. And then Dominic.
>> Yeah. Um I just want to make sure
everybody also understands and realizes
that these are just some best practice
guidelines. It does not actually um
substitute for the practitioners and
facilitators professional work and
opinion and really they need to make
sure that they are doing things while
being patient centric. And so ensuring
for example um just to kind of go back
for a moment to the the people being in
the room you know if someone is
comfortable with that that conversation
should have happened if they want them
standing outside the door you know those
sort of things all should really be done
with the patient and with the patient in
mind and to and and part of the idea on
this is to have the flexibility so that
those different things or aspects can be
utilized including for example um you
know uh any aspects of guiding or
non-guided you know that's really up to
the patient not necessarily something
that should be done just in a best
practice the best practice is talk with
the patient have those conversations in
advance and then it's working with the
patient to ensure within the bounds of
safety of course but that's part of it
what are the different options for the
patient that should be part of the
preparatory sessions is going through
what is going to work for that patient
in that set and setting and so I just
want to make sure that that's clear this
does not you know uh supersede that it's
actually all should be a part of it
thank you
also I realized I just did it again I
didn't post the facilitator monitoring
in the chat.
Perfect.
All righty. Any other questions,
comments, concerns before we move on?
All righty. So, I will go ahead and put
the managing difficulties in the chat
first.
So, managing difficult experiences.
Patients [clears throat] may encounter
emotionally challenging or intense
experiences during administration.
Facilitators must be prepared to provide
supportive interventions including
verbal reassurance, grounding techniques
um encouragement of breathing or
relaxation strategies um and adjustments
to environmental conditions. So for
instance, lighting um someone earlier
mentioned the eye cover um music if they
need help with positioning or anything
like that. And then facilitators must
avoid interventions that unnecessarily
interrupt the patients experience unless
safety concerns arise. We just want to
ensure that they are um allowed to go
through their process while also
recognizing that the um facilitator is
not inherently a um
therapeutic
that's not the right word. They're not a
therapist. So we want to provide things
that they can do um very quickly. So
verbal reassurance, grounding techniques
that can be done. Um encouragement of
breathing or relaxation can be done. Um
or adjustments to environmental
conditions can be done.
But uh I will go ahead and turn over to
Lisa. Your mic has been enabled.
>> Um thanks. Maybe also adding providing
physical support. Um in some cases
clients become nauseous and also having
a hard time standing up and they need
physical assistance even when they sign
um the the form
and opt out from the touch. Facilitator
would still have to provide physical
touch like guide them to a bathroom.
and you muted.
>> Thank you. Um there are going to be
times where we discussed in preparation
that there was going to be uh occasions
where you know that touch consent had to
be
not violated but they needed assistance
outside of what they expected maybe
nausea um whatever it may be. So we have
recommendations for that. So providing
physical support works. Thank you.
All right.
Any other questions, comments, concerns?
All right. So, here are our safety and
emergency procedures. So administration
sessions must include clear protocols
for managing emergencies. Um
facilitators must have access to
emergency medical service contact
procedures, facility emergency
protocols, um fire and environmental
safety procedures, communication systems
for requesting assistance.
If a medical or psychological emergency
occurs, facilitators must prioritize
patient safety and follow established
emergency procedures.
And that's going to vary of course
institution to institution. Um,
and the emergency response plan for
someone that is down the street from a
hospital might be different than someone
who is in rural New Mexico. So I just
wanted to let it they follow whatever
the established emergency procedures are
of the entity which they are working
under.
Right.
So then we have section completion and
recovery.
So at the conclusion of administration
experience, patients must be monitored
until they are stable and capable of
safely leaving the facility.
Facilitators must ensure patients
demonstrate adequate orientation and
physical stability, that they have
access to hydration and rest. Um,
patients understand post session safety
instructions. Patients must be reminded
not to operate a motor vehicle for at
least 12 hours following administration.
Um, and this in the event that people
were split splitting the dose and or
needing to reup, it would be 12 hours
following the last administration. Um,
but those are what we have for session
completion and recovery. Does anyone
have any questions, comments, concerns,
additions?
>> And just a correction, this is Jorge.
Uh, you said 12 hours, but in the
document it says 24.
>> Does it? Oh,
thank you.
>> Yes.
All righty. And then Gregory
>> just figuring out how to push buttons
here.
Um the 12 versus 24. I had a note about
that.
Um
I think the conversation, sorry, let me
get back to my note. Final
administrative prep session 12 hours to
30 days before administration. That's
not the same, is it?
Oh, never mind. That was that was
regarding something else. We shifted 24
to 12 hours on the administration prep.
I confused that.
>> Yeah. So, it was the 12 hours you had to
prep and then Yeah, I remember what
you're talking about. No worries.
So obviously not operating 24 hours
means and we listed it in preparation
but I just want to respecify that they
had a transportation plan beforehand. Um
I'm not expecting these um healing
centers to become hotels. Um, I mean,
some may want to, that might be a draw,
but, um, if they need, they can
establish a transportation plan. Um, we
don't want to have people that are on
psychedelics driving. Well, I don't.
Drivers are bad enough. Um,
and then
we have transition to integration.
So before leaving the facility, patients
should receive guidance regarding the
integration process. They should know
who they're going to um what that's
going to look like. If they um they
should not just be okay, you're
discharged, goodbye. It should be we
have somewhere for you to go. It should
they should encourage reflection on the
experience before um you know their
actual integration. provide information
about scheduled integration sessions,
offer recommendations for post session
self-care. Um that can be rest, that can
be um you know people tend not to eat a
lot when they are on psilocybin. So that
may be going to get a nice meal or other
aspects of self-care. Rehydrating is a
big one. Um but just to en ensure that
they are transitioning out of that
space. But uh Katherine
Yes. Um I am just I think that actually
uh scheduled integration sessions need
to be taken care of before the
treatment. Um maybe confirming their
integration sessions, but I just find
that when people are coming out, that is
the worst time to try to be scheduling
anything or like it's just not the time.
Um, what I usually do is I wait and I
check in the next day and if their
integration wasn't scheduled, which 99%
of the time it is already scheduled, or
if I need to change it for some reason,
like sometimes it's scheduled a few days
out, but if they had an especially hard
journey, I'm going to try to move it up
because I want to get integration
um a little sooner, especially if it was
very challenging or confusing or scary
for them. Um, but I would never do that
while they're coming out of it. I would
wait till the next day and then reach
out and be like, "How are you doing? Uh,
can we schedule this or that?" Anyway,
that that's my two cents.
I completely agree. So, I went ahead and
updated it. Um usually during
preparation patients should schedule and
receive guidance on integration. Um on
the integration process cuz I agree um
anyone that
after a trip should not be responsible
for anything on their calendar. Um,
usually your guidance on the
Denali, you had a question or you put
your hand down, but
>> Oh, I was just going to agree. Um, but
it sounds like I don't need to. There
are also billing reasons that you want
to um you want to you want to schedule
those ahead of time. So for reasons
related to most third party payer
contracts.
>> Yes. All righty. Any other questions,
concerns, comments, additions for
transition to integration.
All righty.
Next part is documentation.
So facilitators must demonstrate admin
or facilitators must document
administration sessions in the patient's
clinical record. Documentation must
include the date and duration of
administration, the identity of the
facilitators present, the dosage
administered, the patients observed, uh
the patient observations during the
session, um any supportive interventions
provided and the confirmation of safe
session completion. Documentation must
also confirm that the patient was
released safety safely. What does that
mean? That means I did not let them go
right after with the keys to their
Toyota Camry. I said, "Do you have a
transportation plan home, which they
should have already done in preparation
um and ensuring that they are going to
be safe for the recovery period after
their session. All righty. Any
questions, comments, concerns?"
Oh, Denali.
Um,
>> sorry, I I don't have a fully formed
thought here. I just want to I want to
be thoughtful about how we require
documentation and how we distinguish
that from like what will be the notes
that are required from billing because
those need to be two different things
like what the department wants to know
um versus what insurance companies um
need to know. So I but I don't have a
recommendation or thought just in
general
something to consider.
So this documentation applies to the
track and trace system. So it's whatever
the department system um that they it's
the clinical record because that one can
transfer between providers very easily
while they're still in the psilocybin
program. So, it would allow that, but it
would not be like what you put on your
health insurance bill. That is
none of my business. Um, I mean, it is,
but it's like not like the specific code
that you use.
That wouldn't be up to the department to
determine. It would be the um,
however they documented it with their
compliance. um stuff. Dominic probably
has a better clarification for me.
>> Uh yeah, I mean that's not actually why
I raised my hand. I thought you were
actually doing just fine with that, Ian.
Um the the one thing I did want to say
just since you had called on me is um
adverse events needs to be included in
this. I just realized that's not listed
there. So um just need to have that
there. But really it does um as far as
the documentation there is also a
difference between what actually gets
sent to the department which is really
going to be very minimal with the
exception of when there are research
studies that people that patients join
in on and then it'll follow the
protocols for those research um uh for
the research studies. Um and then
otherwise this is really their own
clinical records that the that the uh
practitioners and facilitators will need
to keep
just like any other provider.
>> And then Gregory
>> Oh, I was just going to ask Dominic to
say what he just said.
Um
>> I was reading your mind, right? I I do
think it's interesting like like how we
define what goes to department um data
collection for like the program
requirements research and continuous
improvement um like the way that there's
consent for that what system is used all
this stuff is I think still in process
um but then what does actually go to
insurance um I feel like Denali may be
the best person in the room to answer
Uh,
but yeah, I don't know. I'm interested
to see like if there's um any
specification on when we get to that
insurance conversation, how those
records are kept and held and protected
and shared and all that stuff, but I
don't think that really needs to be in
here beyond what Dominic listed.
And then I see Denali
>> and Gregory. I'm not going to answer
that, but I I think um I was thinking
about something else. But I think in
general it would be helpful for the
community to do some education around
billing and those documentation, that
kind of stuff from like an insurance
perspective, but agree that doesn't need
to live in the regulations or with DO. I
was um Dominic mentioned adverse events
and I think um I just wanted to flag I
don't think we have a definition
neither of adverse event neither in the
guidelines or in the draft regulations
and I think it it would be really
helpful to know what that threshold is
for the department otherwise we're just
going to leave it up to practitioners to
decide what is adverse and that doesn't
provide uniformity um in service
[clears throat] of safety those kinds of
like is it when EMS needs to be called?
Is it right? What is the threshold? So,
um I think that's more a reflection on
the draft regulations than it is on
these guidelines.
Personally, and this is not for the
guidance, this is just a personal view.
Adverse events are any
unintended
undesirable
medical occurrence. So like
for instance the most common adverse
effect from
vaccinations
is
um
the needle poke the injection site pain.
Um so it's like
what is the threshold where we are
saying that is
um an adverse event because if we're
counting like the route of
administration that could definitely be
an interesting conversation. Um,
Gregory,
um,
[clears throat] I think from the
research and continuous improvement
group working with Dr. Pitzky on
defining uh, the adverse events
framework for psychedelic assisted
therapy. Um I think a lot of this will
become um concrete and um advisable to
programs to adopt into their
individualized practices. Um I think the
separation of challenging from adverse
will find as somebody noted in chat
earlier um when we have studies
[clears throat]
like Hopkins and UNM etc like over time
with preparation inside the container of
psychedelic assisted therapy especially
with mushrooms
um or psilocybin because people haven't
really done this with whole mushrooms
we will find that there are very very
few adverse effects um
uh but reporting those like I think
people will try to protect themselves by
over reporting and that's fine I think
on the receiving those reports and
filtering that data out that's more of a
department or the responsibility of an
organization like open that like allows
the interpretation of that data
Um,
but yeah, I think it's really important
from like a study standpoint to monitor
all of the challenging experiences, the
mitigation factors, but I think from a
compliance requirement level on the
state side, they just need to know if
somebody like vomited or, you know, had
a heart attack or, you know, I don't
think
honestly like I'm not even sure how we
want to handle nausea cuz I
something that people
experience but it's tends to be expected
and it's also easily mitigated
but
so I guess I will
defer then the definition to
rci I think they have better mechanisms
um than I currently do in my brain for
adverse event categorization.
Um so I will just keep in that they must
document the adverse events and then um
continue to let rci develop their full
you know what is an adverse event that
those definitions and all of that fun
stuff.
And then Gregory is that a new hand or
>> Yeah. Yeah. Just sorry I didn't want to
keep clicking my mic. Um I would like to
see if that language works with the
department um because that would just be
like a deferral like send the definition
over here. Um the other thing I wanted
to point out about the controlled
studies is we are actually entering in a
very different landscape. We are using
whole mushrooms
a variety of education stuff to be
defined and like we are going to be
working with wild data. We're going to
be working with non non non like
uh a patient or a participant class
that's not like curated, right?
Sometimes where the studies succeed in
uh perfection is by design. Um, so just
on the other side of that, like, hey,
maybe we should be like continually
looking for these things.
>> No, for sure.
>> I love Denali's idea for having a
definition.
[laughter]
I have a few.
Um, but yes, I agree. Like get it like
let's nail that definition when it goes
into the rules.
Yep. Um,
all righty.
Questions, comments, concerns about
uh Dominic,
>> Greg, I was just going to say if you
have a uh a draft definition or two, go
ahead and or and Denali, go ahead and
put it in the chat so that we can look
at it um and then see about moving or
including at least a version of it.
And in the event that um
you don't have it off the top of your
head right now.
>> Oh, that was not right.
>> Yeah, you can always send it to us uh
through the email. Um and you're not far
off, Ian. It was just uh there was a
space there.
And for those who aren't reading the
chat, Ian just put the um the program um
email in the chat.
>> And thank you, Greg.
All righty. So, the last thing we have
for this document is timing and clinical
oversight.
So, administration sessions should allow
adequate time for full psilocybin
experience. We shouldn't be sending
people home halfway through. Um programs
must ensure a facilitator to patient
ratio of 1:3. Um and this again means
that we still need the two people in the
building but those two people can have
six patients total. Adequate staffing to
maintain safety compliance with
regulatory and professional standards
and administration must not be rushed or
conducted in a manner that compromises
patient safety or therapeutic integrity.
We don't want to give someone a negative
experience basically. Questions,
comments, concerns.
All righty. And then so I'm going to go
ahead and
offer and say
does anyone do you guys want to vote on
adoption of these administration
sessions or do you want to sit with them
for a little
Gregory,
I personally don't see any reason that
these can't move forward. I'd
[clears throat] love to um see what our
next steps are as well and what the kind
of next like 6 to 8 weeks of
demands from this this group are looking
like.
>> All righty. So, we will go ahead and
move to a vote on the administration
sessions guidance. Uh all those in favor
at this time, please raise your hand.
I see four votes.
>> Four in favor. All opposed or please
lower your hands at this time.
All opposed, please raise your hand.
I see zero
>> with four yeses and zero nos. This has
been adopted.
The next piece of guidance that we are
going to need is going to be the
integration session. So I would just
like to open the floor for the sharing
of ideas. Um what you guys would like to
see before I prepare the document and
what things you think are necessary.
Uh Gregory,
>> let's start with the definition.
Okay. Uh, Denali,
>> hi. I just think um in general and I
think this goes for all of the
committees. I've been trying to think
about the relationship between internal
documents and regulations that go
through rulemaking. It may be helpful
for the full advisory board to adopt a
policy of how and when
guidance regulations are reviewed and
updated. Right? there are things that we
keep in guidance because the evidence is
evolving and the rule making process
isn't really the best place um for for
things to live in regulation. So I but I
want to I want to be sure that we are
also taking advantage of that
flexibility. So um I think what I'm
recommending is that the full advisory
board adopt a policy around how
guidance regulations the the cadence
with which guidance regulations are
reviewed and updated based on new
evidence or based on feedback from from
how they're working in practice.
Sorry, I was writing notes on it. Uh,
yes, definitely. I will look into that.
Uh, Gregory,
>> um, I think that's beautiful. Um, I
think it's global should be like way
beyond the scope of this group, but in
so doing that
um, cadence and trigger clause. So I
think if there's an event that that
people that there's a process of saying
hey should we review this as opposed to
being constrained to simp
often but writing the flexibility is a
good idea.
>> Perfect. Thank you. and Lisa
>> um for the next meeting on integration
I'd love to see the documentation
process of integration sessions
>> and Dominic
>> yeah just a quick note as far as the
cadence I actually uh and I know it's
not necessarily for this committee but
down the road is we actually at the
department utilize as for any protocols
which I would consider the best guidance
documents to be part of uh protocols
really for this purpose is that they
have to be reviewed every year and so
they have to be reviewed on an annual
basis and so just when it comes to that
I would recommend that at a minimum um
that they be reviewed once a year and so
go back to the committees for reviews
changes updates and then uh move forward
from there with the board. So
>> seems reasonable. Thank you.
Uh Gregory,
>> um couple things in response to Dominic.
Um I know that in
uh propagation and testing like we have
SOP requirements. Are we going to have a
similar
um document submission from the clinical
um
bodies like the individual businesses
when they they become permitted? Are we
going to be able to review SOPs from
those organizations and fold those into
that review conversation? Um and then
the other side of the my separate my
reason I act initially rose my hands was
to say
um it would be interesting if we utilize
some of the space that we have in these
groups that aren't like moving hypers
speed forward to uh bring in
a a subject matter expert to talk about
like the details or multiplememes
to talk about um detailed ongoing
integration and what that looks like and
what it really means because I think
when we're talking about harm reduction
and safety for this entire program
that container of integration is a key
aspect to making the whole program
successful. I think this just shouldn't
be taken lightly.
>> Sure. And [clears throat] just to answer
that question, Greg, is um yes,
basically uh healing centers and
approved locations will have to have
their own sets of um SOPs and things
like that. So yeah,
just as a short answer. [laughter]
All righty. Well, does anyone Oh, Lisa.
Um, I'm just wondering if therapy
session would count as an integration.
>> You broke up really bad. Can you repeat
that? I'm so sorry.
>> Oh, sorry about that. Um, I was
wondering if a therapy session would
count as an integration session.
Yes, in if that was part of their their
plan, but typically the person providing
integration would already be a
therapist. So, it would be
at least similar to a therapy session.
They would just be the therapist with
extra
certification on psychedelic.
Gregory
>> um just as a conversation in response to
Lisa's question I think the in the
context of
preparing for it for a session or a
dosing session or whatever you uh part
of that is developing a treatment plan
inside the treatment plan is an
integration plan and I think the
flexibility of like how the individual
team care team defines what integration
steps and milestones are tracked. Um my
perspective integration is like the
whole like what I do in the morning,
what I drink like do I drink water, you
know, like like am I remembering and
processing these things? Do I have like
community groups and family and stuff
like that? like the but the recorded
tracking of integration steps could be
very much like a report that a
self-report from a reflection on a
therapy session once a month but then
also um integration groups or
psychedelic informed body work or you
know like all of the types of things
that really fit for that individual's
process
as a whole human with their own specific
specific needs. But [clears throat]
yeah, defin like in my mind definitely
like therapy like we should all go to
therapy once in a while, right? Like
maybe all the time. Um and if we define
that as a part of our integration then
yeah
I don't know if that helps or
no no I think it's a very uh good point
in in the context that not everyone's
journey is going to look the same. So
not everyone's processing of the journey
is going to look the same. Um and we do
discuss at least in preparation the use
of different modalities. And while I do
think that people need therap a therapy
portion of integration to help them
understand their experience, I also
recognize that there are other
modalities that can help them with
integration and sometimes you know
kinestheology or other mechanisms can
help people to process their journey.
So, um I really appreciate your point,
Catherine.
>> Um yeah, there was a time and I don't
remember which meeting and where it was.
There's so many of these. um where we
had discussed allowing somebody's
therapist to attend
um the ex the treatment even if they're
not a uh qualified you know facilitator
or um or or practitioner um about
bringing them into the process like cuz
sometimes somebody's counselor is
somebody that they trust more than
anybody and if they're coming to us for
this treatment like I I actually try to
incorporate their their current
therapist whenever possible. And I'm
just wondering for integration cuz I
think I think the best scenarios are
when I can hand it off to their
therapist. I do integration. I always
include at least two. Um but then I like
to be able to hand it over to their
regular counselor to continue
integrating and I'll invite their
counselor to be a part of the
integration so that for the handoff. So,
just something to consider. And again, I
don't remember if we decided that
[snorts] their therapists can attend. I
I don't know if that ever got clarified
anywhere, but um anyway, thank you.
>> I don't know that we ever clarified it,
but I don't think we ever excluded
any guest full stop.
So,
I mean, if their therapist wanted to
attend, I I wouldn't see an objection to
that as long as the patient and the
facility consented
>> and as long as they're aware, like they
would have to be prepped, right? Yeah.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. And they would like we wouldn't
just like call their the patient
therapist for them and be like, "Hey,
>> we just brought your friend." Like that
wouldn't happen.
>> Right. Right.
Um, but yes, no, that is a good point
because a lot of pe and
>> anyone who's been through their fair
share of therapists knows it takes a
long time to find a good therapist. Um,
and so yeah, people put a lot of trust
in them. If you've been through 15, 20
different therapists and you're like,
"This one is the one that works for me."
I would see that being beneficial to
have them there. Yeah.
>> Uh, Sky,
>> excuse me. Excuse me, Ian. This is I
need to interrupt for a moment. We are
scheduled until 10 p 10:00 a.m. and
several of us have another meeting right
at this moment. So, I just wanted to
raise your awareness on that.
>> Yes, I am so sorry everyone. I totally
lost track of time. Thank you to the
department and everyone uh who has
attended. If you have any additional
comments, I will still read them. Just
send them to medical.silicyon
doh.nm.gov.
Um and I will respond to all of those. I
appreciate you guys so much for being
here with me this morning and for
working through these this guidance. It
really helps to develop the program and
make it stronger. Thank you guys so much
for showing up on this Tuesday and have
a great rest of your Oh, next meeting.
Thank you.
Thank you, Gregory. You saved me. Um,
why don't we do is the department free
the 27th
>> at the at 9:00 a.m.?
>> Yeah. Uh, Ian, just to to let you know,
both uh Dr. Truckner and myself will
actually be traveling on that day. But
um as long as you are all comfortable
with um Jorge and the rest of the team
uh representing the department, we are
>> um yeah, that's fine.
>> Cool. So it will be on the 27th at 9:00
a.m.
>> That looks good.
>> Oh, can we do the 28th? Hold on. Can the
department do the 28th?
Uh it would be the same
>> the same thing but
>> it was just
>> Yeah. Yeah. Just to let you all know I
mean it would be the same all that week
with uh Dr. Trucker and myself. Um and
the reason why just to let you all know
is we had been invited to uh present and
be at SAMA's um conference which is
addressing data gaps to monitor
expanding use and misuse of psychedelics
in the US. And so, uh, he and I will
actually be, uh, out for that entire
week or when we're back at the end fully
scheduled at this point, unfortunately.
But, um, uh, so same thing falls. But if
the 28th works for Jorge and team,
that's perfectly fine.
>> Yeah. Uh, we are available from 9 to 10.
>> 9 to 10 on the 28th. Can do.
>> Yes.
>> Thank you, Ian.
>> All righty. Well, thank you everyone for
showing up. Have a great rest of your
Tuesday. Be safe out there. Um
especially on those roads. We've talked
about the drivers today, so be safe out
there, guys.
Thank you. Bye.